<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>A comfort against the Spaniard</title>
            <author>Nun, Thomas, 1556 or 7-1599.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1596</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 34 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 11 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-12">2011-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A08430</idno>
            <idno type="STC">STC 18748</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC S119504</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99854711</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99854711</idno>
            <idno type="VID">20148</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A08430)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 20148)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 967:29)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>A comfort against the Spaniard</title>
                  <author>Nun, Thomas, 1556 or 7-1599.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[24] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed by Iohn Windet for I. O[xenbridge],</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1596.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Dedication signed: Thomas Nun minister of the word, at Weston.</note>
                  <note>Publisher's name from STC.</note>
                  <note>The first leaf is blank.</note>
                  <note>Discusses the Armada of 1588 and the English expedition against Portugal in 1589.</note>
                  <note>Signatures: A-C⁴.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the Folger Shakespeare Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Armada, 1588 --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Great Britain --  History --  Elizabeth, 1558-1603 --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Great Britain --  Foreign relations --  Spain --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Spain --  Foreign relations --  Great Britain --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2010-07</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-07</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-09</date>
            <label>Pip Willcox</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-09</date>
            <label>Pip Willcox</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-06</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:20148:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:20148:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>
               <figure>
                  <p>A COMFORT AGAINST THE Spaniard.</p>
                  <q>
                     <bibl>DEVT. 20.</bibl>
                     <p>And when ye are come nigh vnto the battell, the Prieſt ſhal come forth to ſpeake vnto the peole.</p>
                     <p>And ſhall ſay vnto them, Heare, O Iſraell, you are come this day vnto battell againſt your enemies, let not your harts faint, neither feare, nor be amazed, nor in dread of them.</p>
                     <p>For the Lord your God goeth with you, to fight for you againſt your enemies, and to ſaue you.</p>
                  </q>
                  <p>LONDON Printed by Iohn Windet for I. O. 1596.</p>
                  <figDesc>ornamental border</figDesc>
               </figure>
            </p>
         </div>
         <div type="dedication">
            <pb facs="tcp:20148:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:20148:2"/>
            <head>TO THE REVE<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>REND FATHER IN God, William Lord Biſhoppe of
<hi>Norwich, and to the reſt of her</hi> Maieſties Officers for the execution of Iuſtice in that Dioces. T. N. wiſheth grace and peace.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">I</seg>S it true that the Spanyardes will com this ſpring? And is it not as true that we are ready to receiue them? Hath this land at any time had, either better prouiſion, or more Souldiers: brauer Captaines to leade them, or ſounder Diuines to encourage them?</p>
            <pb facs="tcp:20148:3"/>
            <p>Yea, but what for Armour on our backes if feare bee in our hearts? can feare there remaine where our late victories are reme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>bered? Is not our enemie the ſame, our caſe, nay our God the ſame?</p>
            <p>But <hi>Pharao,</hi> and <hi>Siſera,</hi> their o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerthrow is now forgotten. <hi>Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riam</hi> may ſing alone, and <hi>Barac</hi> and
<hi>Debora</hi> can get no hearers. O, ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther let this booke call to mind our dutie, for why ſhould we depriue, either our GOD of his glorie, or our ſelues of ſuch a comfort? Is it not an houres Sermon of that inuincible Nauie, and a briefe Apologie of the Portugale voiage? and doth it not ſet before our eyes how great thinges the Lord hath done for vs? To this ende I haue publiſhed it, &amp; to your Lordſhip, <pb facs="tcp:20148:3"/>and worſhips, I doe Dedicate it. Beſeeching God, ſo to bleſſe you in gouerning vs, that ſtill the Goſpell may haue free paſſage among vs. So ſhal we ſtil eate the fruite of our vines, in deſpite of <hi>Senacherib:</hi> and good
<hi>Ezechias</hi> ſhal not want <hi>Eſaies</hi> to comfort her, whe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <hi>Rabſache</hi> ſhall be ſent to rayle vpon her.</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>Your Lordſhips, and worſhips in Chriſt Thomas Nun Miniſter of the word, at Weſton.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="tract">
            <pb facs="tcp:20148:4"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:20148:4"/>
            <head>A Comfort, againſt the <hi>Spaniarde.</hi>
            </head>
            <epigraph>
               <q>
                  <bibl>
                     <hi>Iud. 5. ver. 19.</hi>
                  </bibl>
                  <p n="19">
                     <hi>19</hi> The Kings came, they fought: then fought the Kings of of Canaan at Taanach by the waters of Megiddo: they got not the money they deſired.</p>
                  <p n="20">
                     <hi>20</hi> From heauen they fought, the ſtarres in their courſes fought againſt Siſera.</p>
                  <p n="21">
                     <hi>21</hi> The riuer Kiſhon ſwept them away, the riuer of their meetings the riuer Kiſhon. O my ſoule treade vnder foot what ſoeuer ſeemeth valiant.</p>
                  <p n="22">
                     <hi>22</hi> Then the horſehoofes were battered by the ſwift fleeing of their valiants.</p>
                  <p n="23">
                     <hi>23</hi> Curſe ye Meroz: (ſaith the Angel of Iehoua) curſe ye the inhabitants thereof, becauſe they came not to helpe Iehouah, to helpe Iehouah among the mighties.</p>
                  <p n="24">
                     <hi>24</hi> Let Iael the wife of Cheber the Kenite be bleſſed aboue women: aboue women dwelling in tents let her be bleſsed</p>

                  <p n="25">
                     <hi>25</hi> He asked water, ſhe gaue him milke: ſhe brought foorth creame in a lordly diſh.</p>
                  <p n="26">
                     <hi>26</hi> She put her left hand to the nayle, and her right hand to the workmans hammer and ſhee ſmote Siſera: ſhee tooke away his head and battered &amp; bruſed his temples.</p>
                  <p n="27">
                     <hi>27</hi> Betweene her feete he bowed himſelfe, he fell &amp; lay ſtill betweene her feete: he bowed himſelfe he fell, and where he bowed himſelfe there he fell depriued of his life.</p>
                  <p n="28">
                     <hi>28</hi> The mother of Siſera looked out at a window, &amp; chat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted through the latteſſe: why doth his chariot defer to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turne? why tarie the wheeles of his chariots?</p> 
                  <pb facs="tcp:20148:5"/>
                  <p n="29">
                     <hi>29</hi> Her wiſe Ladies anſwered her, yea ſhe her ſelfe anſwe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red her owne wordes.</p>
                  <p n="30">
                     <hi>30</hi> Haue they not gotten? doe they not deuide the ſpoyle? A maide, yea two maidens to euery one? Siſera hath a pray of diuers colours, a pray of diuers colours, of colours of nelde worke, of diuers colours of nedle worke on both ſides, for the neckes of the ſpoylers.</p>
               </q>
            </epigraph>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">F</seg>Ather Iacob in his laſt<note n="*" place="margin">Gen
49.21.</note> wil fore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſheweth, that Neptalie ſhoulde be a hind let go, giuing goodly wordes. The ſinger of the ſong (beloued) is the performer of this Prophecie, euen <hi>Barack</hi> of<note n="a" place="margin">Iud, 46.</note> Cadeſh the ſonne of <hi>Abinoam:</hi> for as his feet were ſwift in<note n="c" place="margin">Iud. 4, 10.</note> leauing his armie againſt
<hi>Siſera:</hi> ſo are his words ſweete which for the victorie he here ſingeth with <hi>Deborah.</hi> The whole ſong is lon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger then may now be handled, this part as fitteſt for our purpoſe I haue red vnto you: for wee are heere aſſembled, not onely to ſanctifie this Sabaoth as at o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther times: but alſo to bleſſe God for the late Spani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ards ouerthrow. It containeth 12. verſes, and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiſteth of two members. In the one the battell is de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcribed: in the other a curſe to <hi>Meroz</hi> and a bleſsing to <hi>Iael</hi> is pronounced. Three circumſtances deſcribe the battell: the place wher it was fought: the parties that fought it &amp; the eue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t of it. Two places are named Taanah and Megiddo neighbor townes in half<note n="e" place="margin">Ioſua. 17 11.</note> Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>naſſes. At Megiddo good king <hi>Ioſias</hi> was<note n="*" place="margin">2. King. 23.22. 2. Chron. 35.22.23.</note> ſlaine in the battell, &amp; to Megiddo the three ſpirits like Frogs in the<note n="a" place="margin">Reue. 16.13.</note> Reuelation doe bring the kings of the earth <pb facs="tcp:20148:5"/>to battel: the alluſion is vnto this text, &amp; the mening is, that pſeudocatholikes ſhould fight with no better ſuc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſe againſt Chriſtia<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s, after the reuiuing of the goſpel, then did <hi>Siſera</hi> againſt <hi>Barack</hi> at the waters of Megid<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>do. And in this ſence, well may our narrow Seas bee called the waters of Megiddo, for thither their pride brought them, and ther were they cutin peeces. And thus much for the place, the parties that fought are now to bee conſidered. <hi>Siſera</hi> and his adherents is the one, and <hi>Barack</hi> and his partakers the other. <hi>Siſera</hi> his adherents are thus recorded. <hi>The kings came, they fought: then fought the Kings of Canaan. Ioſua</hi> in conquering the land, killed<note n="c" place="margin">Ioſu. 12.24.</note> one &amp; thirtie of them, Iſrael had expreſſe<note n="e" place="margin">Exod, 23.33. and Deut. 7.2.</note> commandement to roote out the reſt:<note n="a" place="margin">Iud. 1.21.</note> But <hi>Beniamin,</hi>
               <note n="a" place="margin">Iud. 1.28.</note>
               <hi>Zabulon,</hi>
               <note n="a" place="margin">Iud. 1.30.</note> 
               <hi>Aſher</hi> and<note n="a" place="margin">Iud. 1.31.</note> 
               <hi>Neptalie,</hi> thought it better pol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>licie to put the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> to tribute: they preferred gaine before godlines, but what gained they by that pollicie? They found them prickes in their eyes, and thornes in their ſides, as God had<note n="c" place="margin">Numb.
33.55.</note> threatned: they were brought to meere beggerie and extreame ſlauerie, as well they deſerued: meere beggerie, for their high<note n="e" place="margin">Iud. 5.6.</note> waies were vnoccupied, and traficke ceaſed: extreame ſlauerie, for the ſeruant of ſeruantes, euen curſed Canaan became<note n="*" place="margin">Iud. 4.2.</note> Lord ouer the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>. But what is not Canaan his curſe vpo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the Popes backe? Is not he as rightly called the ſeruant of ſeruants as<note n="a" place="margin">Gen. 9.25.</note> Canaa<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> was? If ſo? Why is not his brood rooted out from among vs? Or ſeeing England wil ſtil be pittying of them, why are they not Lords ouer her as was Canaan ouer Iſrael? The difference betweene them is the reaſon of it: for Iſrael choſe new Gods; En<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gland hath renounced I dolatrie, Iſrael did<note n="c" place="margin">Iud. 4.1.</note> euill in the ſight of the Lord: England giueth free paſſage vnto the <pb facs="tcp:20148:6"/>Goſpel. And this I dare aſſure you, that ſo long as Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liſh lawes do countenance true religion, England ſhall be ours in deſpight of Gods enemies. Truth it is, that in ſpace of 339. yeares Iſrael was<note n="e" place="margin">Iud. 3.8. Iud. 3.12. Iud. 4.2. Iud. 6, 1 Iud. 10 7. Iud. 13.1.</note> ſix times oppreſſed: but this alſo is as true that no one oppreſsion began before Iſrael went a whoring after other Gods. The tenne tribes were<note n="*" place="margin">2. King. 17.2</note> carried captiue into Aſhur: but the tenne tribes had firſt 257. yeares continued in the ſin of
<hi>Iero<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>boam.</hi>
               <note n="a" place="margin">2. King. 24.14. &amp; 25.11. 2. Chron. 36.20. Daniel. 1.2,</note> 
               <hi>Iudah</hi> &amp; <hi>Beniamin</hi> were caried to Babel: but not before <hi>Ioſias,</hi> his children had<note n="c" place="margin">2. King. 23.32, &amp; 37. &amp; 24, 9. &amp; 19</note> ouerthrowne what <hi>Io<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſias</hi> had eſtabliſhed concerning religion. And as for their poſteritie which returned from Babel, to builde the temple,<note n="e" place="margin">2. King. 2<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>.2,
2. Chro. 34.2.</note> they became Saduces and Phariſies: they<note n="a" place="margin">Mat, 27.22. Mark, 15.13. Luk. 23.21. Iohn, 19.15.</note> ioyned with the Romaines, to Crucifie Chriſt, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore <hi>Titus,</hi> eitheir ſacked their Cittie, or burned their temple. We reade of <hi>Dauid</hi> that he<note n="c" place="margin">1, King. 15.5.</note> held Religion all his daies, the like we reade of<note n="e" place="margin">1. King. 22.43.</note>
               <hi>Iehoſhaphat,</hi> the like of<note n="*" place="margin">2. King, 18,
3.</note> 
               <hi>Ezechias,</hi> and the like of<note n="a" place="margin">2. King,
22.2.</note> 
               <hi>Ioſias,</hi> and who of all their e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nemies preuailed againſt their land in their daies? And yet to that purpoſe, how often and how dangerouſly were they aſſaulted? Twiſe Philiſtims army was<note n="c" place="margin">1. Chro. 14.11. &amp; 13.</note> pit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ched in Baalperaſim: once Edom, Iſmael, Moab, Am<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon, Philiſtims, Amalakites, Hagarens, Gebalites yea and <hi>Aſhur</hi> too had<note n="e" place="margin">2. Chro. 20.1. &amp;, 2. and Pſal.</note> conſpired together, and were ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proched to Engeddi:<note n="*" place="margin">2. King. 18.17.</note> 
               <hi>Rabſache</hi> had brought his hoſt to the walles of Ieruſalem: and to ſuch a plunge <hi>Necho Pharao</hi> put
<hi>Iudah</hi> that ſhe loſt her<note n="a" place="margin">2. King.
23.29.</note> King in the battell euen good King <hi>Ioſias.</hi> And to come to thoſe ſower<note n="c" place="margin">Reuel. 9.14. vnto. 20.</note> Angels of Gods wrath, I meane the Turkes and Sara<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſins, what though for their multitude, they are c tenne thouſand thouſands: for their force horſes: for their <pb facs="tcp:20148:6"/>courage Lyons heades: for their great deſolation they make burning where they come, they haue Habergi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons fierie blew, and brimſtone, and for their dooing this vpon a word, fire, ſmoke and brimſtone come out of their mouthes: yet Chriſtian nations they ouerrun not, only they kill ſuch men as will bee ſtill<note n="e" place="margin">Reue. 9.20.</note> worſhip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of Deuils, and Idols of gold, ſiluer, ſtone &amp; wood, there onely making deſolation where Gods wrath is prouoked by Idolatrie.</p>
            <p>Salomon was as a Lyons whelpe couched in his denne whileſt hee helde Religion, but after that his thouſand wiues had<note n="*" place="margin">1. King. 12 3.</note> turned his heart, who then had not a hart to riſe vp againſt him? <hi>Hadad, Reſon, Ie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>roboam</hi> how pittifully did they<note n="a" place="margin">1. King. 12.14.23. &amp; 26. verſe</note> afflict him? And at the laſt<note n="c" place="margin">1. King. 1<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>.20.</note> rent in two peeces his kingdome. Iſrael had<note n="e" place="margin">Exod. 34.24.</note> pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſes of her God to be kept ſafe in her land, whilſt ſhe held his ceremonies. His ceremonies we hold whileſt his ſonne we profeſſe, for he is the end of them, &amp; the truth of them, and therfore as ſafe as were the Iſraeli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſh women from the enemie at home, whilſt their huſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bands appeared before God at Ieruſalem: ſo ſafe are we from the Papiſts, whilſt wee hold faſt our profeſsi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on. Salomons temple was ſeauen yeares in<note n="*" place="margin">1. King, 6.38.</note> building,
<hi>Nabuchadnezar,</hi>
               <note n="a" place="margin">2. King. 25, 9.</note> burnt it, he was ſeuen yeares to be a<note n="c" place="margin">Dan. 4, 22,</note> beaſt for it: yet <hi>Daniel</hi> giueth him this<note n="e" place="margin">Dan. 4.24.</note> aſſurance, that if he would breake of his ſinnes by righteouſneſſe, and his iniquities by pittying the poore people, there ſhold be a prolonging of his peace,<note n="*" place="margin">Eliza. 1</note> Our Queene hath broken the necke of Poperie, hath receiued into her kingdome Chriſts righteouſnes, &amp; pittying the poore ſouls of her ignorant ſubiects hath cauſed it to be prea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ched <pb facs="tcp:20148:7"/>among them. And why ſhould wee diſtruſt God for the continuance of our peace, whilſt ſhe and her ſuc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſours continue this courſe? Yea but Moyſes telleth Iſrael, that if they doe not all Gods commandements, the enemies ſhall eate the fruites of their land. Now England is ſo ful of ſinne that in ſteade of al it ſeemeth to performe ſcarcely and one of them.<note n="*" place="margin">Leui. 26.15, 16.</note> The text is, if ye keepe not my commandements but breake my co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uenant then &amp;c. Now England, howſoeuer it faileth in ciuill duties, yet holding the couenant ſhee is not ſubiect to this puniſhment. Neither is ſhee therefore the rather to be ſecure: for wherefore is peſtilence and famine ſo often among vs? Wherefore ſo often is the ſword of the enemie vpon our ſouldiers abroad? The ſword of the magiſtrate vpo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> our malefactors at home? But for her ſinnes. Neither yet anye whit the more is ſhee the to ſpare the Papiſts, for doe they not de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nie the nature &amp; offices of Chriſt? Doe they not giue vnto that<note n="a" place="margin">Reuel. 9.11.</note>
               <hi>Abaddon</hi> what is due vnto our Soueraigne? They are heretiques and in truth very Traytors, &amp; yet you would thinke them the beſt ſubiects, if you conſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der but their dealings with vnreformed miniſters: they are ſo zealous in ſpeeches againſt them, and ſo impor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tunate with Iudges til ſentence be giuen againſt them. But O ye fooles, can ye imagine no other let for bring<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing in againe your ſuperſtitions, but only that the lear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned miniſters their mouthes are ſtill opened? Are the lawes ſo ſoone altered? Will England bee ſo ſoone at your becke, as when with the Dog ſhe returned to the vomite, and with the ſwine to the mire? Hath ſhe theſe 37. yeares hated the whore, left her naked and burnt her with fire, and ſhould ſhe now againe begin to loue <pb facs="tcp:20148:7"/>her? I tel you God hath put theſe things into her heart to doe them, ſtriue not longer againſt his gouerment. Come out of Babell as we haue done, kiſſe his Sonne &amp; then liue in our land, yea liue for euer. But if ſtil you will haue a
<hi>Sauls</hi> eye againſt Gods Embaſſadors: then O ye iudges doe ye Iuſtice, &amp; let not<note n="c" place="margin">Conſer. Ezra. 2.13. with Reuela. 13.18.</note> 
               <hi>Adonicams</hi> chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren ſtand vp againſt them. Are they not<note n="e" place="margin">Reuel. 11.3.</note> two for their fewneſſe and in ſackcloth for their poorenes? Yet out of their mouthes commeth the<note n="*" place="margin">Reuel, 11.5.</note> fire that deuoureth your enemies, they are your<note n="a" place="margin">2. King. 6.17.</note> fathers, and the<note n="c" place="margin">2. King. 2.12.</note> chari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ots and horſemen of Iſrael, they bring vnto you the glad tydings of the Goſpell, which if you belieue, you ſhall<note n="e" place="margin">Ioſu, 3.16.</note> liue for euer, and if you ſtill profeſſe you ſhal ſtil be ſafe from your enemies. And this of <hi>Siſera</hi> his ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>herents. <hi>Barack</hi> is the other partie<note n="*" place="margin">Iud. 4.10.</note> 10000. marched vnder his banner, but who reuenged his quarrel? <hi>From heauen they fought, the ſtarres in their courſes fought againſt Siſera.</hi> Theſe were dumbe creatures, yet ſuch as Ieho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uah vſeth to deſtroy his enemies. At his commaund<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment the waters<note n="a" place="margin">Gen. 7.23.</note> deſtroied the olde world: fire from heauen<note n="c" place="margin">Gen. 19.24.25.</note> Sodome and Gomorrath;<note n="e" place="margin">Exod. 9.24.25.</note> haile and<note n="*" place="margin">Exod, 10, 14, 15.</note> graſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hoppers the fruites and beaſts of Egypt: the red<note n="a" place="margin">Exod, 14.28.</note> Sea
<hi>Pharao</hi> and all his hoſt:<note n="c" place="margin">Ioſu. 10,
11.</note> hay leſtones more of <hi>Ioſuas</hi> e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nemies then did all
<hi>Ioſuas</hi> armie, the Lord of hoſtes is his name. The hoſtes of heauen and earth are alwaies ready preſt for his armies. Had the Spaniard learned this leſſon he would haue trembled to haue giuen the name of God to his Nauie, for onely Iehouah is in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uincible. The Centurion ſheweth by his anſwere how well he beleeued it, <hi>I am not worthie</hi>
               <note n="*" place="margin">Mat, 8.8.</note> ſaith hee to our Sauiour <hi>that thou ſhouldeſt come vnder my roofe, only ſpeak the word and my ſeruant ſhall be healed: for I haue ſouldiours <pb facs="tcp:20148:8"/>vnder me, I ſay to one come and he commeth, and to another goe and he goeth:</hi> As if he ſhould ſay: health, and conſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quently all other creatures are ſo ready to goe &amp; come at thy word, as are my ſouldiers at my co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mandement. But to leaue this point, and to come to the euent of the battell which thus followeth.
<hi>They got not the mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny they deſired. The riuer Kiſhon ſwept them away, the riuer of their meetings, the riuer Kiſhon. Ther were the horſehoofes battered with the ſwift fleeing of their valiants.</hi> And was it any maruaile, though <hi>Siſera</hi> his army was thus foyled? who euer reſiſted God &amp; preuailed? <hi>Daniels</hi> prophane kingdomes could not, yet was Babel among people as a<note n="a" place="margin">Dan.
<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> 4,</note> Lyon among beaſts. The Medes &amp; Perſians ruled ouer 127. nations.
<hi>Alexander</hi> in ſixe yeares well nigh ouerran the whole world, and the kingdome erected by his Captaines was a fearefull and ougly<note n="c" place="margin">Eſter. 1.1.</note> beaſt with ten hornes. Theſe in
<hi>Nebuchadnezars</hi> eyes were as a goodly image, whoſe head was of gold, breaſt &amp; arms of ſiluer, belly of braſſe, and feete of yron: yet for reſiſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing God &amp; abuſing his people, in ſhort time the Lord ſo powned them to<note n="a" place="margin">Dan. 2.34,</note> pouder, that at his comming in the fleſh, ſcarcely a remnant remained of them. And as for Rome, howſoeuer by Gods cloſe prouidence it may remaine for a time, for the holines of <hi>Pilats</hi> vicar to abide in: yet ſeeing ſhe hath<note n="c" place="margin">Mat, 27.26.</note> killed the Lord, bani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhed
<hi>Iohn,</hi> &amp; co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tinually<note n="e" place="margin">Reuel. 17.6. &amp; 18,
24,</note> ſhed the bloud of Gods ſaints, her damnatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> is decreed, ſhe is that<note n="a" place="margin">Numb. 24 24</note> 
               <hi>Chittim</hi> that muſt in the ende periſh. In <hi>Iohns</hi> daies ſhee was called the<note n="c" place="margin">Reuel. 17.18.</note> great Cittie, and rule ouer the Kings of the earth had ſhe: But that great Cittie ſhall<note n="e" place="margin">Reuel,
16.19.</note> drinke of the wine of the cup of Gods furie,<note n="*" place="margin">Reuel. 16.21.</note> haile like talents ſhall fall vpon it, the whore ſhall<note n="a" place="margin">Reuel. 18.8.</note> come to deſtruction, her<note n="c" place="margin">Reuel, 18.15.</note> Mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chants
<pb facs="tcp:20148:8"/>may bewaile her, but none ſhal be able to helpe her. But to returne to <hi>Siſera:</hi> he had<note n="e" place="margin">Iud. 4.3.</note>
900. yron Chari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ots: his Ladies were aſſured that he could not looſe the victorie, how therefore doe they comfort his mother concerning his long tarrying? <hi>Haue they not gotten? doe they not diuide the ſpoile? a maid yea two maides to euery one. Siſera hath a pray of diuers colours, a pray of diuers colours of nedle worke, of diuers colours of nedle worke, on both ſides for the necks of the ſpoylers.</hi> But the<note n="a" place="margin">Pro. 10.28.</note> fooles their hope quick<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly periſhed, for
<hi>Siſera</hi> is now dead, the armie fled and drowned:<note n="c" place="margin">Iere. 6.1<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>.</note> they ſaid peace peace, but ſudaine deſtruc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion came vpon them. And this for the former part of my text. The other is
<hi>Meroz,</hi> curſe &amp; <hi>Iaels</hi> bleſsing. The cauſe of her curſe thus followeth. <hi>Curſe ye Meroz ſaith the Angel of Iehouah, curſe ye the inhabitants therof, becauſe they came not to helpe Iehoua: to helpe Iehouah againſt the mightie. Meroz</hi> durſt not venter a limme to get libertie, ſhe was ſituated ſo nigh the battel and ſo faint hearted, that wel ſhe might be ſome towne in <hi>Iſaſchar,</hi> the only tribe which <hi>Deborah</hi>
               <note n="*" place="margin">Iud. 5.16.</note> vpraideth of aſſelike ſluggiſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes, and which father <hi>Iacob</hi>
               <note n="a" place="margin">Gen. 49.14.</note> foretolde ſhould bee an Aſſe couched vnder two burdens. She onely regarded her commodities, ſo ſhee kept them <hi>Siſera,</hi> or <hi>Iehouah</hi> whome ſhe ſerued ſhe cared not: Luke warme<note n="c" place="margin">Reuel. 3 14.</note> Lao<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dicea was much like her in behauiour, and almoſt the like puniſhment had ſhee, for ſhee<note n="e" place="margin">Reue. 3.16.</note> was ſpewed out of the Lords mouth, and <hi>Meroz</hi> is here accurſed from his mouth<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> And this of
<hi>Meroz</hi> curſe: <hi>Mels</hi> bleſsing thus fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>loweth. <hi>Let Iael the wife of Cheber the Leuite, be bleſſed a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>boue women, aboue women, dwelling in the tents let her bee bleſſed. He asked water, ſhe gaue him Milke, ſhe brought forth Creame in a lordly diſh: ſhe put her lift hand to the nayle, and <pb facs="tcp:20148:9"/>her right hand to the workemans hammer, and ſhe ſmote Si<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſera, ſhe tooke away the head, and battered and bruſed his tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ples. Betweene her feete he bowed himſelfe, he fell, and where he bowed himſelfe, there he fell depriued of his life.</hi> Before wee come to
<hi>Iaels</hi> bleſsing, a word muſt bee ſpoken of her Country and exploit: ſhe was neither Iſraelite nor Canaanite, but a Kenite,<note n="a" place="margin">Iud. 4.4.11.</note> deſcended from<note n="*" place="margin">Exod,
3.1.</note> 
               <hi>Iethro</hi> king of Median Moſes father in law the Kenite.
<hi>Lot</hi> and <hi>Ie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thro</hi> ſhewed the like obedience, the one<note n="a" place="margin">Gen. 14.4</note> left his fathers houſe to goe with
<hi>Abraham,</hi> the other<note n="c" place="margin">Mat, 11, 5</note> left a kingdome to goe with Moſes, and almoſt the like reward founde they for
<hi>Ruth</hi> the daughter of <hi>Lot</hi> was the Lords mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, c and
<hi>Iael</hi> the daughter of <hi>Iethro</hi>
               <note n="*" place="margin">Iud.
4.17.</note> killed the Lords enemie. But why ſhould <hi>Iael</hi> therefore be bleſſed, was hee not in league with her? Did not hee * flie to her houſe for ſuccour? The league was but ciuill and pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uate: But now a<note n="a" place="margin">Iud. 4.</note> publike cauſe is in hand &amp; the Lords battel in fighting, ſhe was to prefer the cauſe of religi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on before her couenant with <hi>Siſera:</hi> Her bleſsing was the very ſame that
<hi>Gabriel</hi>
               <note n="c" place="margin">Luk, 1, 28.</note> beſtowed vpon
<hi>Mary,</hi> for bearing the Lord, this onely excepted that <hi>Mary</hi> is bleſſed among women, but <hi>Iael</hi> aboue women. I will not now diſpute whoſe was the greaſt bleſsing, but this I am ſure of, that they were both ſaued by belie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing, and not by theſe workes, howſoeuer they had a prerogatiue aboue women for them. For this is a ſea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led truth, that wee are ſaued by<note n="e" place="margin">Ephe. 2.8 9.</note> faith, and not by the wokes of the law: Yea, <hi>Mary</hi>
               <note n="*" place="margin">Luk.
1.47.</note> reioyceth in God her Sauiour. The time is paſt: yet a word of the Spaniard; and that by way of compariſon, with the enemie wee haue now in hand. <hi>Siſera</hi>
               <note n="a" place="margin">Iudg. 4 3.</note> had 900. yron Chariots, the Spaniard a Nauie inuincible: <hi>Siſera</hi> with an high
<pb facs="tcp:20148:9"/>hand, came downe to the riuer Kiſhon. The Spaniard brought their Nauy on our natrow Seas with the like affection. In Iſrael none doubted to follow <hi>Barack</hi> but ſuch as misbelieued <hi>Deborah</hi> her prophecie: In Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land none fainted to take armour againſt the Spaniard, but ſuch as knew not the courſe of Gods gouernment.<note n="c" place="margin">Iudg 4.9<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
               </note> 
               <hi>Deborah</hi> went vp with
<hi>Barack</hi> to comfort his Souldi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers. And at Tilberie O
<hi>Elizabeth,</hi> how were thy Soul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diers encouraged at thy preſence? Maide<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>like in attire, thou cameſt vnto them, but warrierlike in behauiour waſt thou among them, voyde of feare was thy coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tenance, and gracious were thy ſpeeches: Mightie was thine armie as was <hi>Baracks,</hi> but Iehouah would haue the glorie as then hee had, his windes reuenged thy quarel. O Iehouah, to thee muſt we ſing, thou waſt our man of warre in that day, the horſe and his rider thou ouerthreweſt in the Sea, thou haſt triumphed valiant<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly: The Spaniard ſaide we will purſue, we will ouer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>take, we will diuide the ſpoyle, our luſt ſhall be ſatisfi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed vppon them: thou bleweſt with thy windes, the depth couered them, they ſunke to the bottome as a ſtone. O Iehouah, ſo let thine enemies periſh, but they that loue thee, let them bee as the Sunne ariſing to his ſtrength.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="apology">
            <pb facs="tcp:20148:10"/>
            <head>The Apologie of the Portingall voyage.</head>
            <p>THe Portingall voyage had a double purpoſe: the one to ſpoyle the K. of Spaine his townes of victuall, the other to weaken his ſtrength of men and ſhipping: and both theſe to this end, that hee being impoueriſhed and weakned at home, the Church in England might without feare ſtill ſerue the Lord Ieſus in holines and righteouſnes. This was no euil mea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning, ſeing God commandeth<note n="*" place="margin">Reuel. 18, 6.</note> to do vnto the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> as they thought to haue done vnto vs: ſeeing alſo Rome is babel which if wee deſtroy we haue ableſsing. One meanes to accompliſh this, was the carrying of the K. of Porting all into his countrie: neither was this a curſed courſe though his Religion bee accurſed: for ſhall we condemne
<hi>Abraham</hi> for<note n="c" place="margin">Gen. 14.24.</note> carrying with him <hi>Anar Eſchol,</hi> and <hi>Mamre</hi> for recoverie of his Nephue
<hi>Lot?</hi> Or<note n="e" place="margin">Gen. 30.7</note> 
               <hi>loſeph</hi> for vſing the helpe of <hi>Pharaos</hi> ſeruantes when bee went to bury his Father? Or<note n="*" place="margin">Nehemi, 27. 8.</note> 
               <hi>Nehemiah</hi> for hauing ayd fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> 
               <hi>Darius</hi> when he returned to Ieruſalem, or<note n="a" place="margin">Acts 23, 7.</note> 
               <hi>Paul</hi> for ſtirring the Pharaſies againſt the Saduces, that he might eſcape with his life? God forbid, ſeeing the auncient Hebrues had alwaies this Chriſtian libertie, to vſe vncleane beaſtes in matters of Phiſicke. It is truth that many of our ſouldiers died in the voyage: but to the godly death is no curſe; and as for the reſt it is a great bleſsing to the land that they neuer returned. It is truth that at Plymmouth God kept his winds fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> fauoring vs a great while, euen vntill the greateſt part of our victuall was ſpent, &amp; many of our ſouldiers weake: but who knoweth whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther this was that we ſhold humble our ſelues vnder his migh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie hand, at the beginning of the enterpriſe: &amp; that we ſhould giue him the whole glory, the victorie being gotten. This I am ſure of, that he that thinketh he laid theſe croſſe vpo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> vs as <pb facs="tcp:20148:10"/>a curſe, becauſe he diſliked the whole action, neuer knew what bleſsing he vouchſafed vs in any one part of the action: In 3. daies he brought vs from the lands end to the coaſt of Spayne: this was no ſmall bleſsing. He gaue firſt into our handes that towne, wher the yere before that inuincible Nauie was gathe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red together, wher a hourſe was builded for the laying vp of the Engliſh treaſure, where a mint was erected to pay the Souldi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers appointed for that voyage, where alſo we found victuall horded vp for the preſent victualing of a new Nauie. This we confeſſed to be a great bleſsing. The exceeding great plentie of wine &amp; victuals we found ther, were notably abuſed to drun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kennes &amp; ſuffetting: &amp; therfore did not God there once make vs miſſe our purpoſe? and euer after ſend leanes euen to the death among vs? Yet ſo in wrath he euer remembred mercy, as ſtill he ſhewed himſelfe a fauourer of the action. He gaue vs courage, ſo that we burned the ſhipping in the harbor, deſtroy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed the Countrie round about the towne, the armie gathered at the Bridge, hauing great aduantage of vs, both of place and number, could not withſtand our forces, they fled before vs to the toppee of ſleepe mountaines, where, if they ſtayed, our ſword pearced them, if they fled, they brake their neckes down ward. If this were not a bleſsing, why was the Generall &amp; his valiant Captaines ſo ioyfully receiued, when in the Euening they returned fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the ſlaughter? yea, why was the next day ſo ſolemly proclaimed <hi>A day of thankeſgiuing.</hi> How rued it the enemie from the high town to behold this triumph? to ſee our Souldiers marching in their armour, our Mariners car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rying abroad their munition and wealth, their owne towne flaming at the laſt with fire, and they not daring come foorth to quench it? And though we thus plagued the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> fiftene daies to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether, yet no other wreak they wrought vpon vs (ſuch a feare had our good God put into theyr hearts) but onely peeping out <pb facs="tcp:20148:11"/>of ſome hole of the Wall, with a peece now and then they took a legge or an arme from vs.</p>
            <p>Penichea was the firſt towne we deſcried in Portingal, and could there, either the ſhot from the Caſtle, or the ſleepnes of the mountaines, or the Rockes hidden in the water, or the troopes of the enemie keepe vs from landing? How ſhameful<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly did they after one or two brauadoes giuen, take themſelues to their heeles? How ſpeedely was the towne giuen ouer and the Caſtle ſurrendered vnto vs? Were there any more of vs then
6000. that marched from thence to Lysborne? Yet as the Hare before the Hounds, ſo fled the peſants before vs. They gaue vs leaue three daies and three nights to enioye the Suburbes of the Cittie, euen ſo long as any prouiſion for vs was found in them. Once indeede they ſallyed out with <hi>Viue Don Antony,</hi> as if they had bene Portingals, but their diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſembling was well recompenced, for we are perſwaded that of 600. not 26. returned without their deadly wound: ſo long the chaſe was in which we had them, and ſo nigh they were when we began to purſue them.</p>
            <p>From Lysborne wee marched in one day to Castcales, the march was long, and our match ſpent, and health ſore decayed, this they knew as well as our ſelues: yet all that day long, durſt they once skirmiſh with vs? Nay, their horſemen thought it as a greate matter, a farre off from ſome high hill to beholde vs; ſo a wonderfull glorie to kill, a few ſtraglers, which the armie being paſſed, they found in Orchards.</p>
            <p>At Caſtcales word was brought that 8000. of them were come within two miles of vs. Wee feared preſently: not that they were come ſo nigh, for the reporter was well rewarded: but least they would not abide the tryall of the battell, ſuch cowards we had alwaies found them, therefore with all ſpeede a Trumpeter was ſent with, round meſſage to prouoke them:
<pb facs="tcp:20148:11"/>we as faſt as we could marching after, they heard no ſooner of our comming, but ſtraight way they tooke themſelues to their flying march, a tricke of warre which they alwaies vſed.</p>
            <p>Homewards within the Iles of Bayon, wee Ancred in deſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pite of them, Vigo and the villages there about we ſet on fire, the inhabitants wee chaſed all, ſome we killed, and had not Bayon bene better walled then they harted, we had fully ſatiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fied our ſelues vpon them: but ſome will ſay: what is the Kinge of Spaine the worſe for this, or we the better? What? we haue laide open the weakenes of his Countrie, the dastardlynes of his people, ſet on fire his holds, &amp; brought away his Munition, his golde, his ſpice: yea, what was there worth the carrying which we left behinde vs? Where wee carried foorth one wee brought home two ſhippes, the like we did of Armour, the like of bread, or at least of Wheate to make bread, and the like of other pillage whatſoeuer is become of it. Yea but our Mariners there all dyed, which are the ſtrength of our land? So indeed doe Papiſts giue out, to diſſwade vnſtable minds from the like enterpriſe, but aske her Maieſties Officers men of great wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip and credite, who ſaw them as they paide them, and they will tell you cleane an other matter. And therefore howſoe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer this voyage is euill ſpoken off of ſome, whome nothing con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tenteth, and bitter to others that loſt their friends: Yet for the Generals and Captaines it was moſt Honourable, for the whole land bleſſed, and curſed for none but for the Papiſtes.</p>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
